Inventory of the Britt Papers 1801-1860
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Britt Papers, 1801-1860.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. Sm. Coll. Britt
38 items.
Papers, 1801-1860, of the Britt family of Pasquotank County, North Carolina. Includes documents, deeds, accounts, and bills of sale for slaves and references to John Cartwright.
Britt Family,; John Cartwright.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 38 items, 12/03/1949.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1801-1860, of the Britt family of Pasquotank County, North Carolina. Includes documents, deeds, accounts, and bills of sale for slaves and references to John Cartwright.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Index Terms
Persons:
Cartwright, John.
Subjects:
Slavery--North Carolina--History.; Real property--North Carolina.; Pasquotank County (N.C.), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Contents List
- Donor Material, 3 December 1949., 3 items. (Folder 1)
- Deed - Devotion White of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, to Dr. John Robertson of Carrituck County, North Carolina, 10 January 1801., 2 pages. (Folder 2)
  Re: Deed of 140 acres in Pasquotank County on waters of Flatly Creek. Consideration $1100. Witnessed by [Reed?]Keaton, Tho. Banks and W. Keaton.
- Order of Court - directing sale of land of John Poole adjoining the lands of Andrew Pendleton near Flatly Creek, Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 10 October 1808., 1 page. DS. (Folder 3)
  To satisfy judgment of William T. Muse against Pool for £ 3.6 and Â£ 0.8 for costs.
- Bill of sale - William T. Muse of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cartwright of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 4 August 1810., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 4)
  Re: Bill of sale of a negro slave, Tom, formerly property of Samuel Riddick, deceased. Consideration $300. Witnessed by Solomon Pool, Jr.
- Deed - Thomas Keaton of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to his brothers Reuben Keaton and Anthony Keaton, 14 September 1812., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 5)
  Re: Deed of Thomas' share in the land on which his father, William Keaton, lives after the death of William. Witness by John An. Freshwater.
- Deed - William Keaton, Senior, of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cartwright of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 4 December 1812., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 6)
  Re: Deed of sale of household furniture and farm produce and animals. Consideration $25. Witnessed by Joseph L. Keaton, and [Wreshwater?].
- Bill of sale - Andrew Knox of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cartwright of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 6 August 1815., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 7)
  Re: Bill of sale of negro boy, Aaron, purchased by Knox at the sale of Ricks Hindley. Consideration $350. Witnessed by Joel Manning and Hugh Knox.
- Receipt - W[illia]m Wilson to John Cartwright, 28 January 1817., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 8)
  Re: Receipt for payment of $650.50 for purchase of a negro man, Edmund, belonging to the estate of Wm. Stolt, deceased, sold on 4 January 1817 to satisfy Stolt's debts. Witness by H. Rerkins.
- Deed - William Wilson to John McDonald, joiner, 6 August 1817., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 9)
  Re: Deed of sale of 18 acres in Pasquotank County, North Carolina on Beaver Dam Swamps, on the southwest side of Newbeginn Creek. Consideration $311. Witnessed by Malachi W. Boushall.
- Grant - State of North Carolina to John Cartwright, 10 December 1818., 2 pages. DS. (Folder 10)
  Re: Grant of 46 acres in Pasquotank County, North Carolina bounded by Forks and Indian Creek, and the land of Ambrose Knox Esq. and Dennis's gut. Entered 4 April 1818. Signed by John Branch, Governor, and William Hill, Secretary. Attached is a plat of the land, surveyed 5 May 1818 by Thomas Dailey.
- Bond - Nehemiah Pendleton and Ambrose Knox to John Cartwright, 19 November 1822., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 11)
  Re: Bond to insure the delivery of negro slaves named in an injunction of the Pasquotank County, North Carolina Court against Cartwright. Witnessed by John C. Ehringhaus.
- Deed - Dempsey B. Pendleton of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cartwright of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 28 January 1823., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 12)
  Re: Deed of sale of a negro man, Tom, for $400. Witnessed by Lemf. Moore.
- Deed - William W. Freshwater and Mary, his wife, to John Cartwright all of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 14 December 1826., 3 pages. ADS. (Folder 13)
  Re: Deed of sale of 10 acres, one-half of Lot No. 2 in the division of land which fell to Freshwater and his wife and William J. Hardy and Nancy, his wife, in consequence of the death of Milicent Lowry, wife of Benjamin Lowry. Witnessed by W. J. Hardy and Jos. H. Pool.
- Draft of Document - John Cartwright and William W. Freshwater, both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 1827., 3 pages. Unsigned draft. (Folder 14)
  Re: Agreement to build jointly a windmill and a house on land of Freshwater.
- Deed - William Gregory, sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cartwright, 5 March 1827., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 15)
  Re: Deed of sale of a tract of land sold at auction to satisfy a debt of $260.22 owed by William S. Bagley. Land was held by Bagley in right of his wife Patsy and formerly belonged to John Robason, deceased. Consideration $68.50. Witnessed by W. W. Freshwater.
- Court order - to the Sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, to sell property of Ambrose Cartwright to settle a debt of $60 owed John Cartwright, 14 September 1832., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 16)
  Signed by Charles Grice, Clerk. Included also is a deed of sale of Joshua A. Pore, Sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, to John Cartwright, of land of Ambrose Cartwright, 4 February 1833. Witnessed by S. Jackson and G. W. Boyd.
- Deed - George W. Boyd of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, to Edmund Blount of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 2 December 1833., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 17)
  Re: Deed of sale of 34 and 1/2 acres and 18 and 3/4 acres, the lands allotted to Nancy McDonald in the division of the estate of John McDonald. Witnessed by A. C. Ehrenghunt.
- Sale - Jonathan B. and Jane B. Lindsy, County of Curituck, to Edmund Blount, County of Pasquotank, North Carolina, 12 September 1834., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 18)
  Re: Sale to Blount of a parcel of land formerly "allotted to Nancy McDonald in the Division of the Estate of John McDonald." This land is part of the Manor Plantation equaling 107 and 9/10 acres in size. Consideration $125. Witnessed by Edward E. Wilson and Timothy G. Cotter.
- Sale - Ambrose Knox to John Cartwright, 20 January 1836., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 19)
  Re: sale to Cartwright of two negro men, Romeo and Ben, for $600. Witnessed by John C. Ehringhaus.
- Sale - Grizzell McDonald to Edmund C. Blount, both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 15 June 1836., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 20)
  Re: Sale to Blount of a parcel of land formerly "allotted to Nancy McDonald in the Division of the estate of John McDonald." This land is part of the Manor Plantation equaling 107 and 9/10 acres in size. Consideration $120. Witnessed by M. U. H. Davis.
- Receipt - Spencer Evans to John Cartwright, 20 January 1837., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 21)
  Re: Evan's receipt of $1000 for a parcel of land formerly held by Spencer's wife, Ann Elizabeth, and Ann's brother, Benjamin L. Broshier. Witnessed by John Cartwright and T. [?] Shannanhoun.
- Receipt - Daniel Tisdale of Elizabeth City, North Carolina to John Cartwright, 5 June 1838., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 22)
  Re: Receipt of $1000 for a negro boy called [Adam?]. Witnessed by Will C. Brooks.
- Sale - of 25 acres of land in Pasquotank County, North Carolina to Edmund C. Blount by Jonathan J. Lin[d?]sy of Tyrell County, 3 May 1839., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 23)
  Consideration $325. Witnessed by William Jackson, and E. L. Stephens.
- Sale - James M. Goodwin, Pasquotank County, North Carolina to John Cavterite, 10 February 1840., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 24)
  Re: Sale to Cavterite of a negro boy, Allen, for $800. Witnessed by Richards Sanders.
- Court order - issued to Joshua A. Pool, sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 21 October 1840., 3 pages. ADS. (Folder 25)
  Re: Directs sheriff to sell the land and tenements of Will and Mary Jordan to satisfy judgment of Thomas Harvey against the Jordan's for payment of indebtedness. Witnessed by A. C. Ehringhaus.
- Sale - J. A. Spruill to John Tweedy, both of Tyrrel County, North Carolina, 4 February 1845., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 26)
  Re: Sale to Tweedy of a parcel of land and Juniper Swamp in Tyrrel County near Muletale Creek. Witnessed by John M. Clus[?].
- Sale - Edmund C. Blount to John Cartwright, both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 29 August 1845., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 27)
  Re: Sale to Cartwright of a parcel of land lying in Pasquotank County, near the headwaters of Fally Creek. Consideration $825. Witnessed by Wm. Charls.
- Sale - Augustus Moon to John Cartwright both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 22 December 1845., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 28)
  Re: Augustus Moon, as executor of the will of Charles R. Kinney, sold to Cartwright a negro man, [Mily?], from the estate of C.R. Kinney for $550. Witnessed by Danl. Richardson.
- Accounts, 1846-1851., 1 page. (Folder 29)
  Accounts between Elizabeth A. Cartwright and John Cartwright, guardian.
- Accounts, 2 May 1846-11 August 1846. (Folder 30)
  Accounts between John Cartwright and Barry Tisdale(?) and receipt by Tisdale and R. White for payment of $77.84 on 12 September [18]46.
- Receipt - W.W. Griffin of Elizabeth City, North Carolina, 25 May 1846., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 31)
  Re: W.W. Griffin acknowledges receipt of $512 from William Jordan also of Elizabeth City for the sale of two parcels of land in Pasquotank County, North Carolina. Witnessed by Joshua A. Pool.
- Accounts, 1 January 1847-1 January 1860., 4 pages. (Folder 32)
  Accounts between William and John Cartwright.
- Deed - Benoni Cartwright to John Cartwright, both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 10 November 1847., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 33)
  Re: Deed of land and premises to John Cartwright. Consideration $30. Witnessed by Nathan Ownman.
- Sale - Simon B. Pool to John Cartwright, both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 31 July 1850., 3 pages. ADS. (Folder 34)
  Re: Sale of land to Cartwright that descended to Pool and his brother, William, from their deceased father. Witnessed by Wm. Simmons.
- Receipt - Barrey Barry's receipt of $750 from John Cartwright, 11 November 1850., 1 page. DS. (Folder 35)
  Re: Receipt for the purchase of a negro slave, Tony, "aged about thirty one years". Witnessed by W.W. Griffin.
- Bond - signed by Jno. Cartwright, Elisabeth City, North Carolina for $200 to establish a scholarship for his sons as a beneficiary to Randolph Macon College, 16 May 1851., 2 pages. ADS. (Folder 36)
- Sale - Barnard Berry to John Cartwright both of Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 24 December 1855., 2 pages. DS. (Folder 37)
  Re: Sale of land to Cartwright for $259. Witnessed by James W. Hunter.
- Sale - George Fox and Cornelia Mead to John Cartwright, 2 December 1857., 1 page. DS. (Folder 38)
  Re: Sale of land to Cartwright for $175. Witnessed by B.F. Keaton and N. Cawlina.
- Receipt - W. R. Spruill's receipt of $3,779.55 from John A. Cartwright in payment of Cartwright's debt, [1 January 1859?]., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 39)
  Witnessed By J. W. Hamlin[?].